MANDANA SAEBI

msaebi@nd.edu . Notre Dame, IN . LinkedIn . Website

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Machine Learning Engineer and Data Scientist with four years of experience in developing novel machine learning models for learning from graph-structured data. Research focuses on Large-scale Graph Analysis, Recommendation, Information Retrieval, Deep Learning, Reinforcement Learning, Meta-Learning, and Language Modeling.

EDUCATION

University of Notre Dame, Notre Dame, IN

Ph.D. in Computer Science, Adviser: Prof. Nitesh Chawla

University of Notre Dame, Notre Dame, IN

M.Sc. in Electrical Engineering, Adviser: Prof. Peter Bauer

Iran University of Science and Tech, Tehran, Iran

B.Sc. in Electrical Engineering

Jan 2017- Present

Overall GPA: 3.8

Sept. 2015 - Dec. 2016

Overall GPA: 3.5

Sept. 2011- May 2015

Overall GPA: 3.6

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Technical Skills: Python (Proficient), R, C++, Spark, Pytorch, Tensorflow, SickitLearn, Keras, Numpy, rdkit, OpenFST, Kaldi, SQL, AWS, MATLAB, AMPL, Tableau, ArcGIS, Latex, Microsoft Office

Certificates: Neural Networks and Deep Learning (Coursera), Sequence Models (Coursera), Building deep learning applications with Keras 2.0 (LinkedIn), NLP with Python for Machine Learning (LinkedIn), Building Recommendation Systems with Python (LinkedIn), Advanced SQL for data scientists (LinkedIn)

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

University of Notre Dame

Jan 2017 – Present

Graduate Research Assistant

- Developed a deep reinforcement learning method for explainable heterogeneous relational reasoning in knowledge graphs (accepted in TKDD).
- Designed a meta learning method for few-shot knowledge graph completion (accepted in EMNLP 2020).
- Improved the prediction of chemical reaction performance by 5% using a deep learning approach by integrating domain expert knowledge and complex molecular graph interactions via LSTMs and graph neural networks.
- Developed a higher-order network embedding method resulting in significant improvement (up to 71.5%) on classification, clustering, and link prediction accuracy over several machine learning algorithms.
- Achieved significant improvement (up to 52.4%) on the task of anomaly detection on synthetic and real-world taxi traffic data by developing a scalable algorithm for detecting anomalies in the large sequential data.

Microsoft June 2021 - Aug 2021

Data Science Intern

Bellevue, WA

Developing a deep learning framework for predicting the optimal bid price for online auction market design.

Apple June 2020 - Sept 2020 Machine Learning Research Intern

Cupertino, CA

Developed a discriminative knowledge graph driven language model resulting in improving speech recognition performance (up to 50% reduction in WER) on named-entities using a scalable, and adaptable approach.

Tala May 2019 - Aug 2019 Data Science Intern Santa Monica, CA

• Implemented a deep learning framework for unsupervised domain adaptation resulting in boosting the target domain predictions with no labeled data up to 5.7%; The model transfers knowledge from a country with rich financial labeled data to another country with no labeled data.

AWARDS & TALKS

- Winner of the ACM Student Research Competition at The Grace Hopper Celebration 2020
- Awarded full travel grant to attend Interspeech 2021
- Awarded full Grace Hopper Scholarship 2019 from AnitaB.org (Sponsored by Boeing)
- Invited talk at KDD 2019 Workshop in Anomaly Detection in Finance, Anchorage, USA Title: Higher-Order Networks for Anomaly Detection
- Awarded full travel grant to attend 2020 CRA Grad Cohort

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

- 1. Saebi, M., Krieg, S., Zhang, C., Jiang, M., & Chawla, N. "Heterogeneous Relational Reasoning in Knowledge Graphs with Reinforcement Learning, (To appear in TKDD)
- 2. Saebi, M., Pusateri, E., Meghawat A., Van Gysel, C., "A Discriminative Entity-Aware Language Model for Virtual Assistants", To appear in INTERSPEECH 2021.
- 3. Saebi, M., Nan, B., Herr, J., Wahlers, J., Wiest, O., & Chawla, N. (2021). "Graph Neural Networks for Predicting Chemical Reaction Performance"
- 4. Zhang, C., Yu, L., **Saebi, M.**, Jiang, M., & Chawla, N. "Few-Shot Multi-Hop Relation Reasoning over Knowledge Bases, In Proceedings of the 2020 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing: Findings (pp. 580-585).
- 5. Saebi, M., Ciampaglia, G. L., Kaplan, L. M., & Chawla, N. V. "HONEM: Learning Embedding for Higher Order Networks", Big Data 8, no. 4 (2020): 255-269.
- Saebi, M., Xu, J., Curasi, S. R., Grey, E. K., Chawla, N. V., & Lodge, D. M. "Network Analysis of Ship-borne Species Introduction and Dispersal in the Arctic", Sci Rep 10, 19558 (2020).
- 7. Saebi, M., Xu, J., Kaplan, L., Ribeiro, B., & Chawla, N. "Efficient Modeling of Higher-Order Dependencies in Networks: From Algorithm to Application for Anomaly Detection", EPJ Data Science 9 (2020): 1-22.
- 8. Zhang, C., Yu, L., **Saebi, M.**, Jiang, M., & Chawla, N. "Multi-Hop Meta Relation Learning for Knowledge Bases", (Under review in TKDE)
- 9. Saebi, M., Xu, J., Grey, E. K., Lodge, D. M., Corbett, J. J., & Chawla, N. "Higher-Order Patterns of Aquatic Species Spread through the Global Shipping Network", PLoS one, 15(7), e0220353.
- 10. Nwanganga, F., **Saebi, M.**, Madey, G., & Chawla, N. "A Minimum-Cost Flow Model for Workload Optimization on Cloud Infrastructure", IEEE CLOUD 2017: 480-487

LEADERSHIP AND SERVICE

- Served as the Research Track program committee member for ECML PKDD 2020.
- Served as the Data Science Committee Member for GHC 2019.
- University of Notre Dame; Social chair of Notre Dame Grad SWE board 2018-2019
- University of Notre Dame; Graduate CSE Engineering mentor 2017-2020
- University of Notre Dame; Graduate student board representative 2018-2020
- Iran University of Science and Tech: Vice president of the Student Scientific Association 2014-2015
- Iran University of Science and Tech; Leader of The Official Robotic Laboratory 2013-2014